<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

    <MetaVariables>
        <Submitter/>
        <Method/>
    </MetaVariables>
    <MetaLinks/>

    <Projects>
        <Project/>
    </Projects>

    <Studies>

        <Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs001487.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs001487.v1.p1" createDate="2017-11-16"
               modDate="2018-01-31">

            <Configuration>
                <Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Sekar Kathiresan, MD</td><td>Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Ida Chen, Ph.D</td><td>LA Biomed at Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, Torrance, CA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>UM1HG008895</td><td>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Instututes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
                <StudyNameEntrez>Center Common Disease Genomics [CCDG] - CVD - TAICHI</StudyNameEntrez>
                <StudyNameReportPage>Center Common Disease Genomics [CCDG] - CVD - TAICHI</StudyNameReportPage>
                <StudyTypes>
                    <StudyType>Observational</StudyType>
                    <StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
                </StudyTypes>
                <Description><![CDATA[
<p>The TaiChi consortium consists of 6 studies that collaborated initially in a large scale metabochip study, and became an ongoing consortium for studies of cardiometabolic disease in the Chinese population in Taiwan. The six studies included the following: 1) SAPPHIRe (Stanford-Asian Pacific Program in Hypertension and Insulin Resistance), a family based study established in 1995 with an initial goal of identifying major genetic loci underlying hypertension and insulin resistance in East Asian populations, with Taiwan subjects participating in the TaiChi consortium; 2) TCAGEN (Taiwan Coronary Artery Disease GENetic), a cohort study that the enrolled patients undergoing coronary angiography or percutaneous intervention at the National Taiwan University Hospital (NTUH) in the setting of either stable angina pectoris or prior myocardial infarction; 3) TACT (TAiwan Coronary and Transcatheter intervention), a cohort study enrolled patients with angina pectoris and objective documentation of myocardial ischemia who underwent diagnostic coronary angiography and/or revascularization any time after October 2000 at the National Taiwan University Hospital (NTUH) (similar to TCAGEN but recruitment was independent of TCAGEN); 4) Taiwan DRAGON (Taiwan Diabetes and RelAted Genetic COmplicatioN), a cohort study of Type 2 diabetes at Taichung Veterans General Hospital (Taichung VGH) in Taiwan, with participants including individuals with either newly diagnosed or established diabetes (subjects with hyperglycemia who did not meet diagnostic criteria for Type 2 DM were not included); 5) TCAD (Taichung CAD study), includes patients with a variety of cardiovascular diseases who received care at the Taichung Veterans General Hospital (Taichung VGH), i.e. specifically individuals who were hospitalized for diagnostic and interventional coronary angiography examinations and treatment; 6) TUDR (Taiwan US Diabetic Retinopathy) enrolled subjects with Type 2 diabetes who received care at Taichung Veteran General Hospital (Taichung VGH), and a small number of subjects from Taipei Tri-Service General Hospital (TSGH); TUDR subjects underwent a complete ophthalmic and fundus examination to carefully document the presence and extent of retinopathy. From these 6 studies, subjects were selected based on completeness of standard metabolic phenotyping and knowledge of cardiac disease status (early onset coronary disease), to undergo whole genome sequencing at the Broad. </p>]]>
                </Description>
                <StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Individuals with coronary disease were identified as those with a history of myocardial infarction, coronary revascularization, or a stenosis of &#8805; 50% in a major epicardial vessel demonstrated by angiography. All cases experienced an early-onset coronary event (men &#8804; 50 years, women &#8804; 60 years) in the context of normal circulating lipid levels (LDL cholesterol &#60; 130 mg/dl or total cholesterol &#60; 185 mg/dl). Controls were enrolled from an epidemiology study and from several Hospital Endocrinology and Metabolism Departments either as outpatients or as their family members. Subjects with a history of CAD were excluded for the controls.</p>]]>
                </StudyInEx>
                <StudyProjects>
                    <Project/>
                </StudyProjects>
                <Attributions>
                    <Header title="Principal Investigators">
                        <AttName>Sekar Kathiresan, MD</AttName>
                        <Institution>Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA, USA</Institution>
                    </Header>
                    <Header title="Principal Investigators">
                        <AttName>Ida Chen, Ph.D</AttName>
                        <Institution>LA Biomed at Harbor-UCLA Medical Center, Torrance, CA, USA</Institution>
                    </Header>
                    <Header title="Funding Source">
                        <AttName>UM1HG008895</AttName>
                        <Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Instututes of Health, Bethesda,
                            MD, USA
                        </Institution>
                    </Header>
                </Attributions>
                <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
                <ConsentGroups>
                    <ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-MULTIPLE_DISEASES-IRB-COL-NPU-RD"
                                  longName="Disease-Specific (Cardiovascular, metabolic disease and associated risk factors, IRB, COL, NPU, RD)"/>
                </ConsentGroups>
            </Configuration>


        </Study>

    </Studies>

</GaPExchange>
